[SPEAKER_00]: So, we often speak about, and it's often mentioned in our talks, things like the one should frequently recollect, you know, like what the Suttas talk about, that you should keep trying to understand, frequently recollect on things, discern the context of your actions, uncover the intentions behind your actions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a... it's obviously... it's like a... it's a... it's a form of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's... there's quite a lot to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, all of that, as we... as we explained, probably, a number of times before, all of that is what the actual right meditation is, or should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you reflect on things,
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're trying to get, you know, to the bottom of something, so to speak, you cannot do that mechanically.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can try, but then, if there is no self-awareness of that process, it's not really going to lead to anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just going to become a dry kind of repetitive mantra or recitation and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: The main property of the correct meditation would be that self-awareness of your thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about trying to get rid of what you think.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're thinking, it's not about indulging what the mind pressures you, what citta pressures you to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about finding a balance between the two, through being aware of what thoughts are present, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, that has, like, many, many layers of development, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of understandable that people, especially in the beginning, need something more palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, your whole experience, everything is geared towards sense objects, geared towards that level of engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, even when things like reflection are heard about, things about, you know, how you should be rightly thinking about things, reflecting and uncovering,
[SPEAKER_00]: That, too, will be approached in that same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so what do I do specifically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I just tell you, well, just reflect on things, for many people it could just sound too abstract, not palpable enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, yeah, but how do I reflect on things?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I do specifically in order to fulfill the requirement of reflecting on things?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they make it into a technique again, make it into a mindless method.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, ironically, asking the question of how do I reflect on things is closer to the right reflection than then following the steps of reflection that you heard about, the methods.
[SPEAKER_00]: But without any self-awareness, that won't be recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people would then move past it and fall on to, again, on something overly defined that will not encourage and maintain the self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, you can't help but feel, OK, I need to do something about the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You come to a channel and then you hear that all the meditation techniques are wrong, so it's like people say, aha, so I shouldn't be meditating.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the past, I used to sit every morning and every evening to meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now I heard...
[SPEAKER_00]: I learned that meditation is wrong, so I shouldn't be sitting in the morning and evening.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... in other talks, I said a number of times, no, if you... if you... if you need a structure, if you need a routine, if you need something that will make you feel like you're doing something about a practice, you can continue sitting in the morning and evening, in the afternoon.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can... whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Five times a day, if you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is not to whether you're sitting or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is what you're doing and what you're expecting to come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you're doing during, for the duration of your sitting, and what do you expect to come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you just sitting as a sense of, like, calming duty or state of mindlessness and... or are you actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Making an active effort to be self-aware, cognizant of whatever is presently enduring and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, if you're practicing, say, if you're keeping the precepts and training in virtue, and then you want to be doing something more proactive, so to speak, not that keeping the precepts is not proactive, but it might not feel like that in the beginning,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's plenty you can do and all of that will revolve around rightly reflecting, correctly reflecting.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that will obviously revolve around just a state of mindlessness and absorption in your sensations and stuff, but plenty of our other talks cover that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, if you need to do something, say, morning, evening or whenever you have a spare time, yeah, sit down quietly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Half an hour, hour, whatever time you have to spare.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you want to be, basically, practicing meditation through asking the right questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Asking the right questions, they would engage the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would result not in you being self-aware only during your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meditation, quote-unquote, time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those those questions, those contexts that those questions point at, would then carry on throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for example, at the end of, say, at the end of every day, you could set time aside, sit down and simply ask yourself, okay, so, for this, like, in this last, I don't know, 12, 16 hours that I've been awake, how did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about finding the right answer or providing the right answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about shedding light onto certain contexts through asking these questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: How did I spend my time throughout the day?
[SPEAKER_00]: And see what's the first thing that pops in your mind when you think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I spent it like this, I spent it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was doing this, I was doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you feel about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be the underlying overall feeling in regard to the question of... well, in regard to the answer that popped up when you asked yourself, how did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be like, could it be better?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't feel quite quite okay, or I feel pleased, I feel displeased.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can go even more specifically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: During this day, last day, during my waking hours, what did I choose to attend to, mostly?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, throughout the day, how often did I choose to attend things on the basis of hindrances, on the basis of desire, on the basis of your will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I act out of those things?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, okay, I didn't act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's good.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, see, you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You knew that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You knew that you didn't act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't stop and think about it, you will not necessarily become self-aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha encouraged in the suttas people, lay people as well, by the way, it wasn't just the monks, to reflect on their virtue, on their unbroken virtue, because the gladness will come out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, oh, yeah, I didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't break the precepts, yeah, but reflect on that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're not doing it for yourself, you're doing it for the citta, you're doing it for the animal, for the wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you ask yourself, how did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: What did I choose to attend to most of the time?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I act out of things?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, recollect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollect, have you... did you act out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you say stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did you do stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: And as you said, if not, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, okay, so did I think about things that I shouldn't have?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I choose to revolve around thoughts that are unbeneficial?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often?
[SPEAKER_00]: How hard was it to say no?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're doing all of this just to to shed light onto your actions, onto your choices, and create that kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the next day comes, when, you know, engaging with life is sort of ongoing, and you have to do this, do that,
[SPEAKER_00]: You will not completely forget, before you choose, say, to engage with hindrances or break the precepts, you won't completely forget that, well, at the end of the day, I will be asking myself about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you gradually sort of increase the weight of that context, the weight of those questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that eventually, just a mere remembrance of the fact that you will be going through this self-interrogation will be enough to, like, no, I won't even do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will highlight the choice of choosing unwholesome, not saying no to your desires when you should have, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you can actually meditate rightly, and you could even make, say, a routine out of it, and still not become dry, mindless, mechanical, technique-based, with a complete loss of any self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, fundamentally, it's choosing the skillful things, and not choosing unskillful things, it's what calms the mind down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what results in samādhi, what results in peace, what results in pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's even when the Buddha was talking to lay people, when he said they should frequently recollect the unbroken virtue, their faith in the Buddha, dhamma and the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, basically reflecting along the lines of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will provide pleasant abiding here and now for them in their household lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the environment that's not necessarily, you know, geared or oriented towards pleasant abiding here and now, in terms of that peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, like, you could just... and you don't even have to be asking the same questions every time, but, obviously, the whole point is, whichever way you were to approach it, you know, different days, different time, but you approach it in regard to your day, in regard to things that you've been concretely doing, choosing, thinking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in regard to, like, theoretical aspects of the paticca-samupāda or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you want to be purifying your actions, and the way to do that is to start shedding light on them, retroactively, acutely, even preemptively, and all of that comes out of, like as I said, investing the effort in first clarifying, then broadening those contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the end, you wouldn't even necessarily have to ask yourself these specific questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's enough just to think about that,
[SPEAKER_00]: And all the right context would be shedding the light, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, sit down, quietly, without disturbances, you know, switch your phone off and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... just a simple basic self-reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: How did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I engage with desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I act out of ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: By body, speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was that beneficial or unbeneficial?
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that make me feel now?
[SPEAKER_00]: And don't forget that you're not seeking for the specific answers.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then make the problem go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're shedding light.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if you're unsure...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know how does that make me feel and I don't quite understand why that is unwholesome or not...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to understand it there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to find the answers to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through asking questions, you have now recognized that you don't understand the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't understand to what extent saying no to desire is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't understand to what extent engaging with hindrances is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you are self-aware now, to certain extent, of the lack of your understanding in regard to certain things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you never stop and thought about those things, you would not... you would just carry on...
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting, choosing, thinking, under the impression that you already know these things, because at some point, when you read them, they made sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they made sense, they reminded you of something that you knew, you made the connections in space and time, and now it's like, oh yeah, I understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: One thing is to, like, intellectually have the idea that represents it, and another thing is to understand
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of which, there is diminishing of craving, diminishing of desire, diminishing of wrong views, diminishing of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what understanding is measured through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through the diminishing and complete absence of dukkha amongst things that used to cause it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how did I spend my day?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I engage with desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I say no to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was I successful or not, overall?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did I choose things that I knew, or maybe I didn't know, but they ended up increasing the desire, increasing the irritation, causing distraction?
[SPEAKER_00]: How often did I do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did I do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why was I not able to say no?
[SPEAKER_00]: What stopped me?
[SPEAKER_00]: What stopped me from exercising the right choice, there and then?
[SPEAKER_00]: And sit with that question even without answering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Seriously, what has stopped me from accessing the right choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: I was aware of it, and I still chose to go with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where did that pressure come from, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did I have to go with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why couldn't I say no?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, different days you might get different answers to the same questions, but the point is,
[SPEAKER_00]: To make the whole thing alive, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can do that if the questions are not abstract, are not dry, mechanical, mantra, recitation.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they pertain to things that you need to think about, that you need to recollect, that you need to bring up, that you need to kind of go through again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the right thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thinking that can actually be purified from the influences of lust, of desire, of irritation, of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could see if that thinking is sufficiently and regularly and diligently developed on the basis of making the right choices throughout the day, on the basis of keeping the virtue and the precepts and training in those principles,
[SPEAKER_00]: You could seek out that thinking would be quite pleasant, quite peaceful, quite imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not afraid of your thoughts anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they have been purified from the influxes of those unskillful, unwholesome, polluting choices that you have been making only because you haven't shed enough light on them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's your meditation, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because every day you'll be doing stuff, every day you'll be choosing things, means every day you could be asking yourself about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And broadening that whole field of self-reflection, whereby the questions can... will eventually become subtler and more and more pertinent to the right things, more acute, more accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it all comes through the principle of the same practice.